[{"question":"<p><strong>A ball is thrown up into the air. At the highest point of its trajectory the ball:&nbsp;<\/strong><\/p>","options":["Is accelerating downwards","Has zero acceleration","Is accelerating upwards","Is still moving upwards"],"answerIndex":2,"examYear":"2015"},{"question":"<p><strong>A ball of mass 200 g moving with a velocity of 8 m\/s collides and sticks with another ball of&nbsp;<\/strong><strong>mass 300 g moving in the same direction with velocity 4 m\/s. What is the common velocity of&nbsp;<\/strong><strong>the balls after the collision?<\/strong><\/p>","options":["5.6 ms<sup>-1<\/sup>","2.8 ms<sup>-1<\/sup>","11.2 ms<sup>-1<\/sup>","1.4 ms<sup>-1<\/sup>"],"answerIndex":1,"examYear":"2015"},{"question":"<p><strong>A boy holds the end of a rubber cord from which hangs a solid metal ball, if the boy whirls the&nbsp;<\/strong><strong>ball in a horizontal circle, keeping his hand still. If the rubber cord breaks when the ball is at a&nbsp;<\/strong><strong>point on the circle, in what direction will the ball move?<\/strong><\/p>","options":["Towards the hand of the boy","Away from the hand of the boy","In the direction of the tangent to the circle at the point of break","None of the above"],"answerIndex":3,"examYear":"2015"},{"question":"<p><strong>A force of 20 N applied parallel to the surface of horizontal table is just sufficient to make a&nbsp;<\/strong><strong>block of mass 4 kg set for motion. Find the acceleration when the force is doubled.&nbsp;<\/strong><\/p>","options":["2 ms<sup>-1<\/sup>","4 ms<sup>-2<\/sup>","5 ms<sup>-2<\/sup>","10 ms<sup>-2<\/sup>"],"answerIndex":3,"examYear":"2015"},{"question":"<p><strong>A man walks 1 km due east and then 1 km due north. His displacement is&nbsp;<\/strong><\/p>","options":["1 km N15<sup>0<\/sup>E","1 km N30<sup>0<\/sup>E","2 km N45<sup>0<\/sup>E","2 km N75<sup>0<\/sup>E"],"answerIndex":3,"examYear":"2015"},{"question":"<p><strong>A motor car moves with a velocity of 20 ms<sup>-1<\/sup> on a rough horizontal road and covers a&nbsp;<\/strong><strong>displacement of 50 m. Find the coefficient of dynamic friction between the type and the&nbsp;<\/strong><strong>ground (g = 10 ms<sup>-2<\/sup>)<\/strong><\/p>","options":["0.3","0.6","0.5","0.4"],"answerIndex":4,"examYear":"2015"},{"question":"<p><strong>A physics student standing on the edge of a cliff throws a stone vertically downward with an initial speed of 10.0 m\/s. The instant before the stone hits the ground below, it is traveling at a speed of 30.0 m\/s. If the physics student were to throw the rock horizontally outward from the cliff instead, with the same initial speed of 10.0 m\/s, what is the magnitude of the velocity of the stone just before it hits the ground?<br \/><\/strong><\/p>","options":["10.0 m\/s","20.0 m\/s","30.0 m\/s","40.0 m\/s"],"answerIndex":3,"examYear":"2015"},{"question":"<p><strong>A quantity is defined as the product of cross-sectional area and change in momentum per unit&nbsp;<\/strong><strong>length. Which of the following is its SI unit?<\/strong><\/p>","options":["Nm","kgs<sup>-1<\/sup>","kgm2s<sup>-1<\/sup>1","Nkgs<sup>-1<\/sup>1"],"answerIndex":3,"examYear":"2015"},{"question":"<p><strong>A rectangular concrete block 40 cm x 30 cm x 60 cm of mass 10 kg rests on a horizontal flat&nbsp;<\/strong><strong>surface. What is the minimum pressure it can possibly exert on the surface?<\/strong><\/p>","options":["816.6 Nm<sup>-2<\/sup>","816. 6 Nm<sup>-2<\/sup>","408.3 Nm<sup>-2<\/sup>","608.4 Nm<sup>-2<\/sup>"],"answerIndex":3,"examYear":"2015"},{"question":"<p><strong>A simple hydrometer consists of uniform cylinder suitably weighted to float upright in most&nbsp;<\/strong><strong>common liquids. It is graduated to read the relative density of a liquid directly. Which of the&nbsp;<\/strong><strong>following is NOT correct?<\/strong><\/p>","options":["When placed in a liquid, it displaces exactly its own weight of the liquid","Its graduation increases from top to base","When placed in a liquid, it displaces exactly its own volume of the liquid","The product of the volume and density of liquid displaced is equal to its mass"],"answerIndex":3,"examYear":"2015"},{"question":"<p><strong>A stone which is dropped into a dry well hits the bottom in 2.2 s. How deep is the well? (Take&nbsp;<\/strong><strong><em>g=10m\/s<\/em>)<\/strong><\/p>","options":["40.4 m","2.4 m","48.4 m","24.2 m"],"answerIndex":4,"examYear":"2015"},{"question":"<p><strong>A woman whose mass is 70 kg sits 2.4 m from the fulcrum of a seesaw. At what distance from&nbsp;<\/strong><strong>the fulcrum should a 60 kg man sit to balance the seesaw?<\/strong><\/p>","options":["2.8 m","2.4 m","3.2 m","3.8 m"],"answerIndex":1,"examYear":"2015"},{"question":"<p><strong>An air bubble trapped at a depth in a liquid rises to the surface. Which of the following is true&nbsp;<\/strong><strong>about its mass and density as it rises?<\/strong><\/p>","options":["Its mass and density increase","Its mass is constant while its density decreases","Its mass and density is constant.","Its mass is constant while its density increases."],"answerIndex":2,"examYear":"2015"},{"question":"<p><strong>Complete the following sentence: The operation of a hydraulic jack is an application of&nbsp;<\/strong><\/p>","options":["Archimedes\u0092 principle.","irrotational flow."],"answerIndex":"0","examYear":"2015"},{"question":"<p><strong>Complete the following statement: Today, the standard meter is defined in terms of&nbsp;<\/strong><\/p>","options":["The distance from the earth\u0092s equator to the north pole.","The wavelength of light emitted from a krypton atom.","The wavelength of light emitted from a sodium atom.","The speed of light."],"answerIndex":4,"examYear":"2015"},{"question":"<p><strong>Convert 30 metre per second to centimeter per minute&nbsp;<\/strong><\/p>","options":["20,000 cm\/min","180,000 cm\/min","120,000 cm\/min","150,000 cm\/min"],"answerIndex":2,"examYear":"2015"},{"question":"<p><strong>During a football match, player A kicks the ball 40 m, 30<sup>o<\/sup> E of S to player B who instantly kicks it&nbsp;<\/strong><strong>30 m, 60<sup>o<\/sup> E of N. What is the magnitude of the resultant displacement of the ball?<\/strong><\/p>","options":["30 m","40 m","50 m","60 m"],"answerIndex":3,"examYear":"2015"},{"question":"<p><strong>How much work is done against gravity in sliding a 500g object through 2 m up a smooth plane&nbsp;<\/strong><strong>that is inclined at 30<sup>o<\/sup> to the horizontal? (g = 9.8 ms-2)<\/strong><\/p>","options":["9.8 J","19.8 J","16.2 J","4.9 J"],"answerIndex":4,"examYear":"2015"},{"question":"<p><strong>If a small body of mass m is moving with angular velocity &omega; in a circle of radius r, what is its&nbsp;<\/strong><strong>kinetic energy?<\/strong><\/p>","options":["m? r","m ? 2r\/2","m ? r2\/2","m ? 2r2\/2"],"answerIndex":4,"examYear":"2015"},{"question":"<p><strong>In free fall, two balls of masses 20 kg and 10 kg were dropped from a height. If the ball with&nbsp;<\/strong><strong>the smaller mass reached the ground after 4 s, what is the difference between the time the&nbsp;<\/strong><strong>two balls reach the ground?<\/strong><\/p>","options":["8 s","2 s","0 s","4 s"],"answerIndex":3,"examYear":"2015"},{"question":"<p><strong>In what distance can a 1,500 kg automobile be stopped if the brake is applied when the speed is 20 m\/s and the coefficient of sliding friction is 0.7 between the tyres and the ground?<br \/><\/strong><\/p>","options":["98.10 m","71.67 m","29.15 m","20.10 m"],"answerIndex":3,"examYear":"2015"},{"question":"<p><strong>The highest point of a simple pendulum bob is 5cm vertically above the lowest point as it&nbsp;<\/strong><strong>swings to and fro between the two extreme ends. At what velocity does it swing past the&nbsp;<\/strong><strong>lowest point (equilibrium point) where the string is vertical?&nbsp;<\/strong><strong>(take g = 10 m\/s2)<\/strong><\/p>","options":["1 m\/s","2 m\/s","5 m\/s","10 m\/s"],"answerIndex":1,"examYear":"2015"},{"question":"<p><strong>Three vectors A, B, and C add together to yield zero: A + B + C = 0. The vectors A and C point in&nbsp;<\/strong><strong>opposite directions and their magnitudes are related by the expression: A = 2C. Which one of&nbsp;<\/strong><strong>the following conclusions is correct?<\/strong><\/p>","options":["A and B have equal magnitudes and point in opposite directions.","B and C have equal magnitudes and point in the same direction.","B and C have equal magnitudes and point in opposite directions.","A and B point in the same direction, but A has twice the magnitude of B."],"answerIndex":2,"examYear":"2015"},{"question":"<p><strong>Which of the following could be measured in the same units as force?&nbsp;<\/strong><\/p>","options":["Energy\/distance","Energy x distance","Energy\/time","Momentum x distance"],"answerIndex":1,"examYear":"2015"},{"question":"<p><strong>Which of the following does not affect the pressure at a point beneath the surface of a liquid?<\/strong><\/p>","options":["Surface area of the liquid.","Density of the liquid","Depth of the point below the surface","Strength of the gravitational field"],"answerIndex":1,"examYear":"2015"},{"question":"<p><strong>Which of the following pairs contains one vector and one scalar quantity?&nbsp;<\/strong><\/p>","options":["Displacement: acceleration","Force : kinetic energy","Momentum : velocity","Power : speed"],"answerIndex":2,"examYear":"2015"},{"question":"<p><strong>Which of the following statements is correct&nbsp;<\/strong><\/p>","options":["Uniform speed always implies uniform velocity","Uniform speed always implies zero acceleration","Uniform speed may imply non-   zero acceleration","Constant momentum implies constant acceleration"],"answerIndex":3,"examYear":"2015"},{"question":"<p><strong>Which of the of the following is a measurement taken with Venier callipers?&nbsp;<\/strong><\/p>","options":["2.0 cm","2.00 cm","2.000 cm","2.0000 cm"],"answerIndex":2,"examYear":"2015"},{"question":"<p><strong>Which of the units of the following physical quantities are derived? I. Area II. Thrust III.&nbsp;<\/strong><strong>Pressure IV. Mass.<\/strong><\/p>","options":["I, II, III and IV","I, II and III only","I, II and IV only","I and II only"],"answerIndex":2,"examYear":"2015"},{"question":"<p><strong>Which one of the following situations is <em>not<\/em> possible?<\/strong><\/p>","options":["A body has zero velocity and non-zero acceleration.","A body travels with a northward velocity and a northward acceleration","A body travels with a constant velocity and a time-varying acceleration.","A body travels with a constant acceleration and a time-varying velocity."],"answerIndex":3,"examYear":"2015"},{"question":"<p><strong>If C is the thermal capacity of a material of mass m and S is its specific heat capacity, then&nbsp;<\/strong><\/p>","options":["C= s\/m","S = Cm","C = Sm","DS = m\/s"],"answerIndex":3,"examYear":"2015"},{"question":"<p><strong>A black car can be more uncomfortably hot on a warm day than a white car because&nbsp;<\/strong><\/p>","options":["It is hot on a warm day","A black object is a better absorber of heat","Black cars have heaters installed in them","White cars have air conditioning systems installed in them"],"answerIndex":2,"examYear":"2015"},{"question":"<p><strong>A little sag is left in overhead telephone wires<\/strong><\/p>","options":["Because taut wires do not conduct sound easily","To allow for the effect of a rise in temperature due to heating effect of current flowing through them.","To allow for the effect of a rise in temperature of the surrounding atmosphere.","To allow for the effect of a fall in temperature of the surrounding atmosphere."],"answerIndex":4,"examYear":"2015"},{"question":"<p><strong>A piece of copper wire of length 100 cm at 30<sup>o<\/sup>C is heated to 120<sup>o<\/sup>C. If its linear expansivity is&nbsp;<\/strong><strong>1.8 &times;10<sup>-4<\/sup>\/ <em>k<\/em>, its new length is<\/strong><\/p>","options":["166.6 cm","101.6 cm","180.6","1.08 cm"],"answerIndex":2,"examYear":"2015"},{"question":"<p><strong>A sample of a monatomic ideal gas is originally at 20&deg;C. What is the final temperature of the&nbsp;<\/strong><strong>gas if both the pressure and volume are doubled?<\/strong><\/p>","options":["5\u00b0C","80\u00b0C","20\u00b0C","899\u00b0C"],"answerIndex":2,"examYear":"2015"},{"question":"<p><strong>A volatile liquid used for cooling purpose in refrigerator is&nbsp;<\/strong><\/p>","options":["Liquid ammonia","Cold water","Liquid nitrogen","Liquid helium"],"answerIndex":1,"examYear":"2015"},{"question":"<p><strong>Complete the following statement: A temperature decrease of 30 C&deg; is equal to a temperature&nbsp;<\/strong><strong>decrease of<\/strong><\/p>","options":["30 F\u00b0.","17 F\u00b0","30 K.","86 F\u00b0."],"answerIndex":4,"examYear":"2015"},{"question":"<p><strong>Complete the following statement: <em>Bimetallic strips<\/em> used as adjustable switches in electric&nbsp;<\/strong><strong>appliances consist of metal strips that must have different<\/strong><\/p>","options":["Mass.","Volume.","Length.","Expansion coefficients."],"answerIndex":4,"examYear":"2015"},{"question":"<p><strong>Heat supplied&nbsp; or removed from a system which&nbsp; causes a change&nbsp; of state without a change in temperature is&nbsp;&nbsp;<\/strong><\/p>","options":["Specific heat","Heat capacity","Latent heat","Boiling heat"],"answerIndex":3,"examYear":"2015"},{"question":"<p><strong>How many atmospheres of pressure must a litre of gas, initially at a pressure of 1 atmosphere and temperature&nbsp;-20<sup>o<\/sup>C, be after it has&nbsp; been compressed to&nbsp;&frac12; litre at 40<sup>o<\/sup>C?<\/strong><\/p>","options":["2.47 atm.","4.5 atm","8.0 atm","3.8 atm"],"answerIndex":1,"examYear":"2015"},{"question":"<p><strong>On a cold day, a good conductor X feels&nbsp; colder to the torch than a poor conductor Y because<\/strong><\/p>","options":["Y retains more heat than X","The temperature of X is lower than that of Y","X conducts heat from the body  less rapidly than Y","X transfers heat from body more rapidly than Y"],"answerIndex":4,"examYear":"2015"},{"question":"<p><strong>The boiling point of water does not depend on&nbsp;<\/strong><\/p>","options":["The impurites in waater","The external pressure","The quantity of water","All of the above"],"answerIndex":3,"examYear":"2015"},{"question":"<p><strong>The ice and steam points of a local liquid in glass thermometer are 10 a and 90a respectively.&nbsp;<\/strong><strong>What will the thermometer read when the temperature is 30 <sup>0<\/sup>C ?<\/strong><\/p>","options":["40a","38a","36a","34a"],"answerIndex":4,"examYear":"2015"},{"question":"<p><strong>The lower and upper fixed points on a thermometer are 40 and 120 respectively. Its reading at&nbsp;60<sup>o<\/sup>C is&nbsp;<\/strong><\/p>","options":["60","40","160","88"],"answerIndex":4,"examYear":"2015"},{"question":"<p><strong>The pressure exerted by a given mass&nbsp; of gas in a container&nbsp;<\/strong><\/p>","options":["Decreases if the container is heated","Increases if the molecules of  the gas move faster","Increases if the volume of the container is doubled","Decreases as the kinetic energy of the gas molecules increases"],"answerIndex":2,"examYear":"2015"},{"question":"<p><strong>The temperature in an electric iron is regulated by&nbsp;<\/strong><\/p>","options":["Thermometer","Bimettalic strip","Steel","Conductor"],"answerIndex":2,"examYear":"2015"},{"question":"<p><strong>Water has an anomalous behavior between&nbsp;0<sup>o<\/sup>C and 4<sup>o<\/sup>C. Which of the following is&nbsp; correct ?<\/strong><\/p>","options":["Mass of water increases between 0<sup>o<\/sup>C and 4<sup>o<\/sup>C","Density of water decreases between 0<sup>o<\/sup>C and 4<sup>o<\/sup>C","Volume of water increases between 0<sup>o<\/sup>C and 4<sup>o<\/sup>C","Volume of water decreases between 0<sup>o<\/sup>C and 4<sup>o<\/sup>C"],"answerIndex":4,"examYear":"2015"},{"question":"<p><strong>What is the Celsius equivalent of 50.0&deg; F?&nbsp;<\/strong><\/p>","options":["10\u00b0","20\u00b0","30\u00b0","40\u00b0 C"],"answerIndex":1,"examYear":"2015"},{"question":"<p><strong>When water is heated in a glass vessel, the level first falls and then rises because&nbsp;<\/strong><\/p>","options":["The apparent expansion of the water is initially  small and later  increases.","There is anomalous expansion of  water","The glass vessel does not expand.","Glass vessel expands first before water stars a more rapid expansion"],"answerIndex":4,"examYear":"2015"},{"question":"<p><strong>Which of the following quantities of water has undergone the greatest change from its heat&nbsp;<\/strong><strong>content at melting point?<\/strong><\/p>","options":["0.5 kg of water at 3<sup>0<\/sup>C","0.2 kg of water at 8<sup>0<\/sup>C","0.005 kg of water at 80<sup>0<\/sup>C","0.1 kg of water at 12<sup>0<\/sup>C"],"answerIndex":2,"examYear":"2015"},{"question":"<p><strong>Which would cause a more serious burn: 30 g of steam or 30 g of liquid water, both at&nbsp;100&deg;C; and why is&nbsp; this so ?<\/strong><\/p>","options":["Water, because it  is denser than steam.","Steam, because of its specific heat capacity.","Steam, because of  its  latent heat of vaporization.","Water, because its specific heat is  greater than that of steam."],"answerIndex":3,"examYear":"2015"},{"question":"<p><strong>A certain radioactive element has a half life of 20 years. How long will it take the activity to become &frac14; of its original?<\/strong><\/p>","options":["20 years","40 years","60 years","80 years"],"answerIndex":2,"examYear":"2015"},{"question":"<p><strong>A plane progressive wave is represented by <em>y<\/em> 2sin 100 <em>t<\/em> 2 <em>x<\/em> where all the symbols have their usual meanings. What is the velocity of the wave?<\/strong><\/p>","options":["500 m s<sup>-1<\/sup>","400 m s<sup>-1<\/sup>","200 m s<sup>-1<\/sup>","100 m s<sup>-1<\/sup>"],"answerIndex":1,"examYear":"2015"},{"question":"<p><strong>A point on a stationary wave where there is no movement of the medium is called&nbsp;<\/strong><\/p>","options":["Node","Antinode","Note","Amplitude"],"answerIndex":1,"examYear":"2015"},{"question":"<p><strong>A uniform wave has a speed of 10m\/s and a period of 0.5 s. The distance between two nearest&nbsp;<\/strong><strong>crests is<\/strong><\/p>","options":["0.2 m","20 m","2 m","5 m"],"answerIndex":4,"examYear":"2015"},{"question":"<p><strong>As transverse wave moves through a medium, the particles of the medium&nbsp;<\/strong><\/p>","options":["Vibrate in a path parallel to the path of the wave","Do not move","Vibrate in a path perpendicular to the path of the wave","Vibrate at an angle of 60o to the path of the wave"],"answerIndex":3,"examYear":"2015"},{"question":"<p><strong>The sound heard after the reflection of sound wave from a plane surface is known as&nbsp;<\/strong><\/p>","options":["Echo","Refraction","Vibration","Revibration"],"answerIndex":1,"examYear":"2015"},{"question":"<p><strong>Which of the following properties is not common to all waves?&nbsp;<\/strong><\/p>","options":["Reflection","Interference","Diffraction","Polarization"],"answerIndex":4,"examYear":"2015"},{"question":"<p><strong>Which of the following statements is true about electromagnetic waves?&nbsp;<\/strong><\/p>","options":["They are longitudinal","They can be seen","They have the same frequency in vacuum","They travel at the same speed in a vacuum"],"answerIndex":4,"examYear":"2015"},{"question":"<p><strong>Which one of the following statements concerning electromagnetic waves is false?&nbsp;<\/strong><\/p>","options":["Electromagnetic waves are longitudinal waves.","Electromagnetic waves are longitudinal waves.","The existence of electromagnetic waves was predicted by Maxwell.","Electromagnetic waves can propagate through a material substance."],"answerIndex":2,"examYear":"2015"},{"question":"<p><strong>Which one of the following statements concerning waves is false?<\/strong><\/p>","options":["A wave can have both transverse and longitudinal components.","A wave carries energy from one place to another","A wave does not result in the bulk flow of the material of its medium","A transverse wave is one in which the disturbance is parallel to the direction of travel."],"answerIndex":4,"examYear":"2015"},{"question":"<p><strong>A light sensitive area at the back of the eye where images are formed is called&nbsp;<\/strong><\/p>","options":["Yellow Spot","Iris","Ciliary Muscle","Retina"],"answerIndex":4,"examYear":"2015"},{"question":"<p><strong>A luminous object is placed at a given distance from a converging lens of focal length 12cm and&nbsp;<\/strong><strong>a real image is produced. Find the image distance if it is equal to the object distance.<\/strong><\/p>","options":["6cm","3cm","12cm","24cm"],"answerIndex":4,"examYear":"2015"},{"question":"<p><strong>An object is placed 15 cm in front of a concave mirror of radius 40 cm.&nbsp;The image formed is<\/strong><\/p>","options":["Virtual and 60 cm behind the mirror","Real and 60 cm in front of the mirror","Virtual and 40 cm from the mirror","At infinity"],"answerIndex":2,"examYear":"2015"},{"question":"<p><strong>How far from a concave mirror of radius 120 cm must an object be placed such that its erect&nbsp;<\/strong><strong>image is four times its natural size?<\/strong><\/p>","options":["72 cm","64 cm","45 cm","50 cm"],"answerIndex":3,"examYear":"2015"},{"question":"<p><strong>How many images are formed when an object is placed in front of two plane mirrors that are&nbsp;<\/strong><strong>inclined at angle 30o to each other?<\/strong><\/p>","options":["0","6","11","12"],"answerIndex":3,"examYear":"2015"},{"question":"<p><strong>Professor Peters walks directly toward a plane mirror at a speed of 0.25 m\/s. Determine the speed of the image relative to him.<br \/><\/strong><\/p>","options":["0.13 m\/s","0.50 m\/s","0.25 m\/s","0.75 m\/s"],"answerIndex":2,"examYear":"2015"},{"question":"<p><strong>The angle of incidence in a denser medium when the angle of refraction in the less dense medium is 90&deg; is called a<br \/><\/strong><\/p>","options":["Critical angle","Reflected angle","Incident angle","Emergent angle"],"answerIndex":1,"examYear":"2015"},{"question":"<p><strong>The driving mirror is a&nbsp;<\/strong><\/p>","options":["Plane mirror","Convex mirror","Concave mirror","Thick plane Mirror"],"answerIndex":2,"examYear":"2015"},{"question":"<p><strong>The following are types of a converging lens except<\/strong><\/p>","options":["Biconvex","Plano-convex","Mini-convex","Converging meniscus"],"answerIndex":3,"examYear":"2015"},{"question":"<p><strong>When the Sun, the earth and the moon are in line during their movement, with the earth being&nbsp;<\/strong><strong>the opaque object and casting its shadow on the moon, we have<\/strong><\/p>","options":["Lunar eclipse","Total eclipse","Partial eclipse","Annular eclipse"],"answerIndex":1,"examYear":"2015"},{"question":"<p><strong>Which of the following instruments could be used in finding angle of elevation of the sun?&nbsp;<\/strong><\/p>","options":["Periscope","Telescope","Kaleidoscope","Sextant"],"answerIndex":4,"examYear":"2015"},{"question":"<p><strong>Which of the following optical instruments does not depend on the use of plane mirrors?&nbsp;<\/strong><\/p>","options":["Kaleidoscope","Simple microscope","Sextant","Simple periscope"],"answerIndex":2,"examYear":"2015"},{"question":"<p><strong>Which of the following statements supports the assumption that light travels in straight lines?<\/strong><\/p>","options":["Light can be diffracted","Light can be reflected","A source of light produces interferences patterns on a suitably placed screen","A source of light produces distinct shadows of opaque objects"],"answerIndex":4,"examYear":"2015"},{"question":"<p><strong>Which of the following is correct about nuclear fission? It is:&nbsp;<\/strong><\/p>","options":["The splitting of a heavy nucleus into two or more lighter particles","An agent used to slow down neutrons in a controlled atomic chain reaction","Combing light atomic nuclei to form heavy","The spontaneous disintegration occurring in the nucleus of certain atoms"],"answerIndex":1,"examYear":"2015"},{"question":"<p><strong>A light energy E falls on a metal and the electrons with a maximum kinetic energy of 0.2eV are ejected. If the work function of the metal is 0.3eV, what is the value of E? <br \/><\/strong><\/p>","options":["0.10eV","0.06eV","0.50eV","1.50eV"],"answerIndex":3,"examYear":"2015"},{"question":"<p><strong>A nucleus is unstable if&nbsp;<\/strong><\/p>","options":["It has two or more isotopes","Its binding energy is not sufficient to hold nuclear particles together.","It is very light with very low density","It has no significant mass."],"answerIndex":2,"examYear":"2015"},{"question":"<p><strong>A radioactive substance has a half life of 4 years. If its activity today is 200 dps, its activity in 8&nbsp;<\/strong><strong>years from today is<\/strong><\/p>","options":["50 dps","25 dps","20 dps","10 dps"],"answerIndex":1,"examYear":"2015"},{"question":"<p><strong>A substance has a half-life of 3min. After 6min, the count rate was observed to be 400.What&nbsp;<\/strong><strong>was its count rate at zero time?<\/strong><\/p>","options":["2400","200","1200","1600"],"answerIndex":4,"examYear":"2015"},{"question":"<p><strong>An element and its isotopes differ only in the number of&nbsp;<\/strong><\/p>","options":["Electrons","Neutrons","Protons","Irons"],"answerIndex":2,"examYear":"2015"},{"question":"<p><strong>Complete the following sentence: When electrons from a heated filament accelerate through&nbsp;<\/strong><strong>vacuum toward a positive plate,<\/strong><\/p>","options":["Only an electric field will be produced.","Only a magnetic field will be produced.","Electromagnetic waves will be produced.","longitudinal waves will be produced."],"answerIndex":3,"examYear":"2015"},{"question":"<p><strong>Radioactive elements are <\/strong><\/p>","options":["Chemically reactive elements","Noble elements","Rare earth elements","Elements that spontaneously emit radiation"],"answerIndex":4,"examYear":"2015"},{"question":"<p><strong>Upon which one of the following parameters does the energy of a photon depend?&nbsp;<\/strong><\/p>","options":["Mass","Polarization","Amplitude","Frequency"],"answerIndex":4,"examYear":"2015"},{"question":"<p><strong>Which of the following is NOT true about cathode ray?&nbsp;<\/strong><\/p>","options":["It moves in a straight line","It causes fluorescence","It possesses a negative charge","It can produce  -particles"],"answerIndex":4,"examYear":"2015"},{"question":"<p><strong>Who proposed the planetary model of the nucleus?&nbsp;<\/strong><\/p>","options":["J. J Thomson","Albert Einstein","Ernest Rutherford","Marie Curie"],"answerIndex":3,"examYear":"2015"},{"question":"<p><strong>X- rays cannot be used<\/strong><\/p>","options":["To take photographs of bone structure in the body","To detect finger prints","To detect flaws in metal castings","To detect flaws in metal castings"],"answerIndex":2,"examYear":"2015"},{"question":"<p><strong>1 farad is equivalent to:&nbsp;<\/strong><\/p>","options":["1 coulomb\/volt","1 volt\/coulomb","1 joules\/coulomb","1 ampere\/sec."],"answerIndex":1,"examYear":"2015"},{"question":"<p><strong>A 0 - 10mA galvanometer with a coil resistance of 30 ohm can be converted to a 0-10A&nbsp;<\/strong><strong>ammeter by using<\/strong><\/p>","options":["0.03ohm series resistor","9.99ohm shunt resistor","0.03ohm shunt resistor","9.99ohm series resistor"],"answerIndex":3,"examYear":"2015"},{"question":"<p><strong>A battery has an internal resistance of 4 and an emf of 12V. The terminal voltage when a load&nbsp;<\/strong><strong>of 20 &Omega; is connected across it is:<\/strong><\/p>","options":["4","10 V","20 V","2 V"],"answerIndex":2,"examYear":"2015"},{"question":"<p><strong>A conducting sphere has a net charge of&nbsp; 4.8&nbsp; 10 <sup>17<\/sup> C. What is the approximate number of&nbsp;<\/strong><strong>excess electrons on the sphere if the fundamental natural charge is -1.6 x 10<sup>-19<\/sup>C?<\/strong><\/p>","options":["100","300","200","400"],"answerIndex":2,"examYear":"2015"},{"question":"<p><strong>A magnet cannot be demagnetized by&nbsp;<\/strong><\/p>","options":["Heating","Hammering","Chemical treatment","The use of solenoid through which an alternating current is flowing"],"answerIndex":3,"examYear":"2015"},{"question":"<p><strong>An a.c voltage is connected to an RLC series circuit of resistance 5 ?, inductance 3 mH and a&nbsp;<\/strong><strong>capacitance of 0.05 &micro;F. Calculate the resonance frequency.<\/strong><\/p>","options":["11.0 kHz","12.0 kHz","13.0 kHz","14.0 kHz"],"answerIndex":3,"examYear":"2015"},{"question":"<p><strong>An electric heater converts 1KJ of electrical energy to heat energy every 2 second with 100%&nbsp;<\/strong><strong>efficiency. The power produced is<\/strong><\/p>","options":["0.5 KW","2 KW","1 KW","10 W"],"answerIndex":1,"examYear":"2015"},{"question":"<p><strong>Complete the following statement:&nbsp;<\/strong><strong>The electromotive force is<\/strong><\/p>","options":["The maximum potential difference between the terminals of a battery","The force that accelerates electrons through a wire when a battery is connected to it.","The force that accelerates protons through a wire when a battery is connected to it.","The maximum capacitance between the terminals of a battery."],"answerIndex":1,"examYear":"2015"},{"question":"<p><strong>If a charged body is moving in a circle on a horizontal plane, what is the general direction of&nbsp;<\/strong><strong>the resulting magnetic field?<\/strong><\/p>","options":["In the plane of the circle.","At an angle 45<sup>0<\/sup> to the plane of motion.","Along the perpendicular axis through the center of the circle.","Along the tangent to the circle."],"answerIndex":3,"examYear":"2015"},{"question":"<p><strong>If a resistor is halved in magnitude and the potential across it is tripled, then the ratio of the&nbsp;<\/strong><strong>old current to the new current is<\/strong><\/p>","options":["1:3","3:1","6:1","1:6"],"answerIndex":4,"examYear":"2015"},{"question":"<p><strong>The angle between the earth&rsquo;s magnetic field and the horizontal is called angle of&nbsp;<\/strong><\/p>","options":["Declination","Dip","Variation","Inclination"],"answerIndex":2,"examYear":"2015"},{"question":"<p><strong>The basic difference between the galvanometer and the electric motor is&nbsp;<\/strong><\/p>","options":["The size of the magnetic fields","The presence of hair springs in the galvanometer","The soft iron armature in the galvanometer","The couple formed on the parallel sides of the rectangular coil in the"],"answerIndex":2,"examYear":"2015"},{"question":"<p><strong>The electromotive force is in such a direction as to oppose the motion or charge producing it.&nbsp;<\/strong><strong>This is a statement of<\/strong><\/p>","options":["Faraday\u0092s Law","Lenz Law","Maxwell Law","Ampere\u0092s law"],"answerIndex":2,"examYear":"2015"},{"question":"<p><strong>The potential difference across the ends of a wire is doubled in magnitude. If Ohm&rsquo;s law is&nbsp;<\/strong><strong>obeyed, one of the following statements concerning the resistance of the wire is true?<\/strong><\/p>","options":["The resistance is one half of its original value.","The resistance is twice its original value","The resistance is not changed","The resistance increases by a factor of four."],"answerIndex":3,"examYear":"2015"},{"question":"<p><strong>The process of adding impurity to a semiconductor to increase its conductivity is called&nbsp;<\/strong><\/p>","options":["Doping","Annealing","Heating","Hardening"],"answerIndex":1,"examYear":"2015"},{"question":"<p><strong>Which if the following combinations consists of intrinsic properties of materials&nbsp;<\/strong><\/p>","options":["Volume and density","Density and mass","Resistance and resistivity","Density and resistivity"],"answerIndex":3,"examYear":"2015"},{"question":"<p><strong>Which of the following can be measured with a potentiometer:&nbsp;<\/strong><\/p>","options":["Emf of a secondary cell","Resistivity of a wire","Potential difference across a conductor","Resistance of a wire"],"answerIndex":1,"examYear":"2015"},{"question":"<p><strong>Which of the following devices is odd in the list ?&nbsp;<\/strong><\/p>","options":["Thermocouple","Potentiometer","Generator","Solar cell"],"answerIndex":2,"examYear":"2015"},{"question":"<p><strong>Which of the following is an essential physical property of the wires used for making fuses?&nbsp;<\/strong><\/p>","options":["High thermal conductivity","Low density","Low melting point","Low electrical resistivity"],"answerIndex":3,"examYear":"2015"},{"question":"<p><strong>Which one of the following statements concerning the magnetic force on a charged particle in &nbsp;a&nbsp;<\/strong><strong>magnetic field is true?<\/strong><\/p>","options":["It is a maximum if the particle is stationary","It is a maximum if the  particle moves parallel to the field.","It acts in the direction of motion for a positively charged  particle."],"answerIndex":3,"examYear":"2015"},{"question":"<p><strong>What is the dimension for velocity?<\/strong><\/p>","options":["ML","LT-1","MT","L-2"],"answerIndex":2,"examYear":"2015"},{"question":"<p><strong>A car moving ith a velocity of 20m\/s at 30o to the horizontal, what is the components of the velocity along the horizontal<\/strong><\/p>","options":["17.3m\/s","10m\/s","20m\/s","21m\/s"],"answerIndex":1,"examYear":"2015"},{"question":"<p><strong>A bullet of mass 20g travelling horizontally at 100m\/s, embeds itself in the centre of a block of wood 1kg which is suspended by light vertical string 1m, calculate the velocity<\/strong><\/p>\n<p>&nbsp;<\/p>","options":["51\/100 m\/s","100\/51 m\/s","101\/50 m\/s","21\/50 m\/s"],"answerIndex":2,"examYear":"2015"},{"question":"<p><strong>A car X moving of mass 500kg accelerates at 1ms-2 when the force due to engine is 600N<\/strong><\/p>","options":["200N","300N","234N","100N"],"answerIndex":4,"examYear":"2015"},{"question":"<p><strong>Starting from rest a car of mass 1000kg accelerates ste dily to 20m\/s in 10 sec , what is the average power developed?<\/strong><\/p>","options":["0.2kw","4.0kw","10kw","20kw"],"answerIndex":4,"examYear":"2015"},{"question":"<p><strong>Which of the following pairs has one vector and one scalar quantity?<\/strong><\/p>","options":["Displacement, acceleration","Potential energy, work","Speed, power","Kinetic energy, force"],"answerIndex":4,"examYear":"2015"},{"question":"<p><strong>If p is the momentum of an object, then the expression P2 \/m has the same units as&nbsp;<\/strong><\/p>","options":["Acceleration","Energy","Force","Impulse"],"answerIndex":2,"examYear":"2015"},{"question":"<p><strong>A ship floating in clear water of density 1000kg moves to sea-water of density 1050kg where it floats, the upthrust on the ship then<\/strong><\/p>","options":["Stays constant","Decreases","Increases","Increases by 0.05 times"],"answerIndex":1,"examYear":"2015"},{"question":"<p><strong>If two equal charges each 1C were sepa ated in air by distance of 1km, what would be the force between them<\/strong><\/p>","options":["2KN","3KN","9KN","10KN"],"answerIndex":3,"examYear":"2015"},{"question":"<p><strong>A steady current of 0.5A flows through a wire, how much charge passes through the wire in one minute?<\/strong><\/p>","options":["32C","23C","12C","30C"],"answerIndex":4,"examYear":"2015"},{"question":"<p><strong>Determine the potential difference between the ends of a wire of resistan e 5&Omega; if 72o C passes through it per minute.<\/strong><\/p>","options":["70V","60V","65V","80V"],"answerIndex":2,"examYear":"2015"},{"question":"<p><strong>For an AC circuit at resonance it means:<\/strong><\/p>","options":["XL = XC","X=L","R=C","Z=R-C n"],"answerIndex":1,"examYear":"2015"},{"question":"<p><strong>The image obtained with a converging lens is upright and three times the length of the object, if the focal length of the lrns is 20cm Calculate the object distance<\/strong><\/p>","options":["13.3cm","40cm","33.1cm","40.3cm"],"answerIndex":1,"examYear":"2015"},{"question":"<p><strong>Which of the followings are the characteristics of light rays:<\/strong><\/p>\n<p><strong>Reflection<\/strong><\/p>\n<p><strong>Refraction<\/strong><\/p>\n<p><strong>D<\/strong><strong>ispersion<\/strong><\/p>\n<p><strong>Condition<\/strong><\/p>\n<p><strong>Chromination<\/strong><\/p>","options":["1 and 2","1 and 3","2 and 3","1, 2 and 3"],"answerIndex":4,"examYear":"2015"},{"question":"<p><strong>The two commonly used lenses in an Astronomical telescope are:<\/strong><\/p>","options":["Objective, diverging","Eye-piece, covering","Objective, eye-piece","Objective, converging"],"answerIndex":3,"examYear":"2015"},{"question":"<p><strong>In dispersion of light rays which is odd out of followings:<\/strong><\/p>\n<p><strong>It involves separation of colours<\/strong><\/p>\n<p><strong>Separation is due to differences in speeds<\/strong><\/p>\n<p><strong>All colours travel with the same speed in vacuum<\/strong><\/p>\n<p><strong>No speed is involved<\/strong><\/p>","options":["1 only","2 only","3only","1,2 and 3"],"answerIndex":4,"examYear":"2015"},{"question":"<p><strong>Sound waves and light waves cannot both be<\/strong><\/p>","options":["Refracted","Reflected","Made to produce an interference","Polarised"],"answerIndex":4,"examYear":"2015"},{"question":"<p><strong>Which of the statements below are correct about threshold wavelength of a metal<\/strong><\/p>\n<p><strong>Increases with frequency of light<\/strong><\/p>\n<p><strong>Decreases with frequency of light<\/strong><\/p>\n<p><strong>Increases ith light intensity<\/strong><\/p>","options":["1 only","2 only","3 only","None of the above"],"answerIndex":4,"examYear":"2015"},{"question":"<p><strong>In order to remove the error of parallax when taking measurements with a metre rule, the eyes should be focused<\/strong><\/p>","options":["slantingly towards the left of the markings","slantingly towards the right of the markings","vertically downwards on the markings","vertically upwards on the markings"],"answerIndex":3,"examYear":"2011"},{"question":"<p><strong>A load is pulled at a uniform speed along a horizontal floor by a rope at 45<sup>o<\/sup> to the floor. If the force in the rope is 1500N, what is the frictional force on the load?<\/strong><\/p>","options":["1524N","1350N","1260N","1061N"],"answerIndex":4,"examYear":"2011"},{"question":"<p><strong>If a freely suspended object is pulled to one side and released, it oscillates about the point of suspension because the&nbsp;<\/strong><\/p>","options":["acceleration is directly proportional to the displacement","motion is directly away from equilibrium point","acceleration is directly proportion to the square of the displacement","velocity is minimum at the equilibrium point"],"answerIndex":3,"examYear":"2011"},{"question":"<p><strong>A block and tackle is used to raise a load of 250N through a vertical distance of 30m. What is the efficiency of the system if the work done against is 1500J?<\/strong><\/p>","options":["62.55%","73.3%","8.33%","94.3%"],"answerIndex":3,"examYear":"2011"},{"question":"<p><strong>If a load of 1kg stretches a cord 1.2cm, what is the force constant of the cord?<\/strong><\/p>","options":["866Nm<sup>-1<\/sup>","833Nm<sup>-1<\/sup>","769Nm<sup>-1<\/sup>","667Nm<sup>-1<\/sup>"],"answerIndex":2,"examYear":"2011"},{"question":"<p><strong>The pressure at any point in a liquid at rest depends only on the <\/strong><\/p>","options":["depth and the density","mass and the volume","quantity and the surface area","surface area and the viscosity"],"answerIndex":1,"examYear":"2011"},{"question":"<p><strong>A balloon whose volume is 300m<sup>3<\/sup> is filled with hydrogen. If the density of air is 1.3kgm<sup>-3<\/sup>, find the upthrust on the balloon<\/strong><\/p>","options":["3000N","3800N","3900N","4200N"],"answerIndex":3,"examYear":"2011"},{"question":"<p><strong>Clinical thermometers are examples of&nbsp;<\/strong><\/p>","options":["pressure gas thermometer","resistance thermometer","alcohol thermometer","mercury-in-glass thermometer"],"answerIndex":4,"examYear":"2011"},{"question":"<p><strong>Two metals P and Q are heated throught the same temperature difference. If the ratio of the linear expansivities of P to Q is 2:3 and the ratio of their length if 3:4 respectively, the ratio of the increase in lengths of P to Q is <\/strong><\/p>","options":["1:2","2:1","8:9","9:8"],"answerIndex":1,"examYear":"2011"},{"question":"<p><strong>A body of weight WN rests on a smooth plane inclined at an angle ?<sup>o<\/sup> to the horizontal. The component of the weight down the slope is<\/strong><\/p>","options":["Wsin&theta;","Wcos&theta;","Wtan&theta;","-Wsec&theta;"],"answerIndex":1,"examYear":"2010"},{"question":"<p><strong>A body of mass 100g moves with a velocity of 10.0ms<sup>-1<\/sup> and collides with wall after the collision the body moves with a velocity of 2.0ms<sup>-1<\/sup> in the opposite direction. The change in momentum is<\/strong><\/p>","options":["8.0Ns","1.2Ns","12.0Ns","1.80Ns"],"answerIndex":2,"examYear":"2010"},{"question":"<p><strong>A 12v battery supplying a current of 20A was used to melt 1.5kg of ice at 0<sup>o<\/sup>C. Calculate the time required if the latent heat of fusion of ice is 336x10<sup>3<\/sup>J\/kg<\/strong><\/p>","options":["35.0min","3.5min","76min","21.0min"],"answerIndex":1,"examYear":"2010"},{"question":"<p><strong>The light from the sun reaches the earth mainly by&nbsp;<\/strong><\/p>","options":["convection","conduction","radiation","reflection"],"answerIndex":3,"examYear":"2010"},{"question":"<p><strong>One valid assumption of kinetic theory of gases is that:<\/strong><\/p>","options":["the molecules are in random motion and the number of collisions is constant","the number of molecules increases with the pressure","the molecules of the gas are all identical and are very small in size","the number of molecules increases with temperature"],"answerIndex":3,"examYear":"2010"},{"question":"<p><strong>An astronomical telescope is said to be in normal adjustment when the&nbsp;<\/strong><\/p>","options":["eye is accomodated","focal length of objective lens is longer than that of the eye piece","final image is at the near point of the eye","final image is at infinity"],"answerIndex":4,"examYear":"2010"},{"question":"<p><strong>Dispersion of light by a glass prism is due to the&nbsp;<\/strong><\/p>","options":["different hidden colours of the glass","different speeds of the various colours in glass","defects in the glass","high density of glass"],"answerIndex":2,"examYear":"2010"},{"question":"<p><strong>A battery of internal resistance of 2&amp;#8486; has a voltage of 4.0V when supplying a current of 2.0A. Calculate the terminal voltage if it now supplies a current of 3.0A<\/strong><\/p>","options":["2.0V","6.0V","1.5V","12.0V"],"answerIndex":2,"examYear":"2010"},{"question":"<p><strong>The purpose of a dielectric material in a parallel plate capacitor is to&nbsp;<\/strong><\/p>","options":["increase its capacitance","decrease its capacitance","insulate the plates from each other","increase the magnetic field between them"],"answerIndex":1,"examYear":"2010"},{"question":"<p><strong>The name of an atom is associated with its atomic number Z, mass number A and neutron number N. Therefore:<\/strong><\/p>","options":["A=Z+N","Z=A+N","N=A+Z","A=N-Z"],"answerIndex":1,"examYear":"2010"},{"question":"<p><strong>A nuclear reaction initiated by adding neutron is called<\/strong><\/p>","options":["nuclear fission","nuclear fusion","nuclear enrichment","radioactivity"],"answerIndex":2,"examYear":"2010"},{"question":"<p><strong>A hydrometer is an instrument used for measuring the&nbsp;<\/strong><\/p>","options":["depth of water in a vessel","relative density of a liquid by method of floatation","relative density of a liquid by finding the apparent loss in weight","relative humidity of the atmosphere"],"answerIndex":2,"examYear":"2009"},{"question":"<p><strong>A bead travelling on a straight wire is brought to rest at 0.2m by friction. If the mass of the bead is 0.01kg and the coefficient of friction between the bead and the wire is 0.1, determine the work done by friction from a height of 10m on top of a platform 0.8m above the ground. Its velocity on reaching the platform is&nbsp;(g=9.8ms<sup>-2<\/sup>)<\/strong><\/p>","options":["2x10<sup>-4<\/sup>J","2x10<sup>-3<\/sup>J","0.2x10<sup>1<\/sup>J","0.2x10<sup>2<\/sup>J"],"answerIndex":2,"examYear":"2009"},{"question":"<p><strong>A mass of gas 7<sup>o<\/sup>C and 70cm of mercury has a volume of 1200cm<sup>3<\/sup>, determine its volume at 27<sup>o<\/sup>C and a pressure at 75cm of mercury<\/strong><\/p>","options":["1200cm<sup>3<\/sup>","1378cm<sup>3<\/sup>","4320cm<sup>3<\/sup>","4629cm<sup>3<\/sup>"],"answerIndex":1,"examYear":"2009"},{"question":"<p><strong>A motor tyre is inflated to pressure of 2.0 x 10N\/m<sup>2<\/sup> when the temperature of air is 27<sup>o<\/sup>C what will be the pressure at 87<sup>o<\/sup>C assuming the volume does not change?<\/strong><\/p>","options":["2.6x10<sup>5<\/sup>Nm<sup>-2<\/sup>","2.4x10<sup>5<\/sup>Nm<sup>-2<\/sup>","2.2x10<sup>5<\/sup>Nm<sup>-2<\/sup>","1.3x10<sup>5<\/sup>Nm<sup>-2<\/sup>"],"answerIndex":2,"examYear":"2009"},{"question":"<p><strong>A beam of light is incident from air to water at an angle of 30. Find the angle of fraction if the refractive index of water is 4\/3<\/strong><\/p>","options":["15<sup>o<\/sup>","18<sup>o<\/sup>","22<sup>o<\/sup>","240<sup>o<\/sup>"],"answerIndex":3,"examYear":"2009"},{"question":"<p><strong>Find the frequencies of the first three harmonics of a Piano string of length 5cm, if the velocity of the waves in the string is 120m\/s<\/strong><\/p>","options":["12000HZ, 2400HZ, 3600HZ","1800HZ, 3600HZ, 5400HZ","800HZ, 1600HZ, 2400HZ","3600HZ, 1800HZ, 900HZ"],"answerIndex":1,"examYear":"2009"},{"question":"<p><strong>The resistance of a piece of wire of length 20cm and cross-sectional area 8x10<sup>6<\/sup>m<sup>2<\/sup> and respectively 4x10<sup>7<\/sup>&amp;#8486;m is<\/strong><\/p>","options":["1x10<sup>-14<\/sup>&#8486;","10.0&#8486;","400.0&#8486;","1.6x10<sup>-13<\/sup>"],"answerIndex":4,"examYear":"2009"},{"question":"<p><strong>An electric device is rated 2000W, 250V. The correct fuse railing of the device is&nbsp;<\/strong><\/p>","options":["8A","9A","7A","6A"],"answerIndex":1,"examYear":"2009"},{"question":"<p><strong>Determine the inductive reactance when a 30.0mH inductor with negligible resistance is connected to a 1.3KHz oscillator<\/strong><\/p>","options":["39.0&#8486;","122.5&#8486;","245.0&#8486;","39K&#8486;"],"answerIndex":3,"examYear":"2009"},{"question":"<p><strong>The half life a radioactive element is 9days. What fraction of atoms has decayed in 50days?<\/strong><\/p>","options":["1\/16","1\/4","1\/2","15\/16"],"answerIndex":2,"examYear":"2009"},{"question":"<p><strong>The graphite rods surrounding the uranium fuel rods in a nuclear reactor are used to<\/strong><\/p>","options":["absorb the neutrons and hence halts the nuclear process","create the neutrons and hence slows down the nuclear process","slow down the neutrons and hence slow down the nuclear process","speed up the neutrons and hence speed up the nuclear process"],"answerIndex":3,"examYear":"2009"},{"question":"<p><strong>A car of mass 1500kg goes round a circular curve of radius 50m at a speed of 40m\/s<sup>2<\/sup>. The magnitude of centripetal force on the car is<\/strong><\/p>","options":["1.2x10<sup>2<\/sup>N","1.2x10<sup>3<\/sup>N","4.8x10<sup>2<\/sup>N","4.8x10<sup>4<\/sup>N"],"answerIndex":4,"examYear":"2008"},{"question":"<p><strong>The efficiency of a machine is always less than 100% because<\/strong><\/p>","options":["work output is always greater than work input","load lifted is always greater than the applied effort","effort applied is always greater than mechanical advantage","velocity ratio is always greater than the mechanical advantage"],"answerIndex":4,"examYear":"2008"},{"question":"<p><strong>Which of these statements is not true? Thermostats are used to control the temperature of&nbsp;<\/strong><\/p>","options":["pressure cookers","laundry irons","hot water storage tanks","aquaria for tropical fish"],"answerIndex":4,"examYear":"2008"},{"question":"<p><strong>A given mass of an ideal gas occupies a volume V at a temperature T and under a pressure P. If the pressure is increased to 2P and the temperature reduced to 1\/2T, then the percentage change in volume of the gas is&nbsp;<\/strong><\/p>","options":["25%","75%","300%","1%"],"answerIndex":1,"examYear":"2008"},{"question":"<p><strong>The thermometric property of a constant volume thermometer is<\/strong><\/p>","options":["change in pressure","change in length","differential expansion","change in volume"],"answerIndex":1,"examYear":"2008"},{"question":"<p><strong>The combination of sound waves with different frequencies is known as<\/strong><\/p>","options":["interference","diffraction","superposition","resonance"],"answerIndex":3,"examYear":"2008"},{"question":"<p><strong>Which of the following characteristics of a wave is used in the measurement of the depth of the sea?<\/strong><\/p>","options":["refraction","reflection","diffraction","interference"],"answerIndex":1,"examYear":"2008"},{"question":"<p><strong>Which of the following eye defects can be corrected using a cylindrical lens?<\/strong><\/p>","options":["astigmatism","presbyopia","chromatic aberration","myopia"],"answerIndex":1,"examYear":"2008"},{"question":"<p><strong>The resistance of a wire depends on<\/strong><\/p>","options":["the length of the wire","the arc of the wire","the temperature of the wire","all of the above"],"answerIndex":4,"examYear":"2008"},{"question":"<p><strong>A dynamo primarily converts<\/strong><\/p>","options":["mechanical energy into electrical energy","electrical energy into kinetic energy","potential energy into kinetic energy","kinetic energy into potential energy"],"answerIndex":1,"examYear":"2008"},{"question":"<p><strong>Which of the following may be found in light nuclei?<\/strong><\/p>\n<p><strong>i. B-particles<\/strong><\/p>\n<p><strong>ii. Protons<\/strong><\/p>\n<p><strong>iii. Neutrons<\/strong><\/p>\n<p><strong>iv. A-particles<\/strong><\/p>","options":["i and ii only","i and iii only","i and iv only","ii and iii only"],"answerIndex":4,"examYear":"2008"},{"question":"<p><strong>The different between X-rays and&nbsp;&amp;#7527;-rays is that<\/strong><\/p>","options":["X-rays arise from energy changes and are due to electrons while &#7527;-rays come from the nucleus","X-rays are electromagnetic radiations while &#7527;-rays are not","X-rays have higher frequencies than &#7527;-rays","X-rays are more penetrating than -rays"],"answerIndex":1,"examYear":"2008"},{"question":"<p><strong>When an atom loses or gains a charge, it becomes<\/strong><\/p>","options":["an electron","an ion","a neutron","a proton"],"answerIndex":2,"examYear":"2008"},{"question":"<p><strong>The distance traveled by a particle starting from rest is plotted against the square of the time elapsed from the commencement of motion. The resulting graph is a measure of<\/strong><\/p>","options":["initial displacement","initial velocity","acceleration","average velocity"],"answerIndex":3,"examYear":"2007"},{"question":"<p><strong>Two points on a velocity time graph have coordinates (5s,10m\/s) and (20s, 20m\/s). Calculate the mean acceleration between the two points<\/strong><\/p>\n<p>&nbsp;<\/p>","options":["2.5m\/s<sup>2<\/sup>","5.5m\/s<sup>2<\/sup>","1.5m\/s<sup>2<\/sup>","0.5m\/s<sup>2<\/sup>"],"answerIndex":3,"examYear":"2007"},{"question":"<p><strong>Which of the following statements are correct?<\/strong><\/p>\n<p><strong>I. Land and sea breezes are natural convection<\/strong><\/p>\n<p><strong>II. The vacuum in a thermos flask prevents heat loss due to convection only<\/strong><\/p>\n<p><strong>III. Convection may occur in liquids or gases but not in solids<\/strong><\/p>","options":["I and II only","II and III only","I and III only","I, II and III only"],"answerIndex":3,"examYear":"2007"},{"question":"<p><strong>The property of the eye known as its power accommodation is controlled by the<\/strong><\/p>","options":["pupil","virtreous humour","iris","cilliary muscles"],"answerIndex":4,"examYear":"2007"},{"question":"<p><strong>Under constant tension and constant mass per unit length, the note produced by a plucked string is 500Hz when the length of the string is 0.9m. At what length is the frequency 150Hz<\/strong><\/p>","options":["3m","0.27m","8.33m","6740m"],"answerIndex":1,"examYear":"2007"},{"question":"<p><strong>An object is placed in front of two plane mirrors inclined at an angle &amp;#952;<sup>o<\/sup>. If the total number of images formed is 7, find the value of 0<\/strong><\/p>","options":["30<sup>o<\/sup>","45<sup>o<\/sup>","51<sup>o<\/sup>","90<sup>o<\/sup>"],"answerIndex":2,"examYear":"2007"},{"question":"<p><strong>The north pole of a magnet can never be separated from the South pole because of a property known as<\/strong><\/p>","options":["magnetic dipole","magnetic moment","magnetic monopole","magnetic quadru pole"],"answerIndex":1,"examYear":"2007"},{"question":"<p><strong>The terminal voltage of a battery is 4.0V when supplying a current 2.0A and 2.0V when supplying a current of 3.0A. The internal resistance of the battery is<\/strong><\/p>","options":["0.5","1.0","2.0","4.0"],"answerIndex":3,"examYear":"2007"},{"question":"<p><strong>The primary aim in high tension transmission is to&nbsp;<\/strong><\/p>","options":["minimize electrical energy losses due to heat production","increase the rate of energy transfer by using high voltage","increase the current in the wires","generate electrical current and low voltage"],"answerIndex":1,"examYear":"2007"},{"question":"<p><strong>A light of energy 5eV falls on a metal and the electrons with a maximum kinetic energy of 2eV are ejected. The work function of the metal is<\/strong><\/p>","options":["0.4eV","2.5eV","3.0eV","7.0eV"],"answerIndex":"0","examYear":"2007"},{"question":"<p><strong>Which of the following is a set of vectors?<\/strong><\/p>","options":["force, mass and momentum","acceleration, velocity and momemtum","mass, weight and density","mass, volume and density"],"answerIndex":2,"examYear":"2006"},{"question":"<p><strong>A catapult used to hold a stone of mass 500g is extended by 20cm with an applied force F. If the stone leaves with an applied force of 40ms<sup>-1<\/sup> the value of F is?<\/strong><\/p>","options":["40 x 10<sup>2<\/sup>Nm<sup>-2<\/sup>","2.0 x 10<sup>2<\/sup>N","4.0 x 10<sup>3<\/sup>Nm<sup>-2<\/sup>","4.0 x 10<sup>4<\/sup>N"],"answerIndex":2,"examYear":"2006"},{"question":"<p><strong>A parachute attain a terminal velocity when<\/strong><\/p>","options":["its density is equal to the density of air","the viscous force of the air and the upthrust completely counteract its weight","it expands as a result of reduced external pressure","the viscous force of the air is equal to the sum of the weight and upthrust"],"answerIndex":2,"examYear":"2006"},{"question":"<p><strong>An electrical heater is used to melt a block of ice, mass 1.5g. If the heater is powered by a 12v battery and current of 20A flows through the coil, calculate the time taken to melt the block of ice at 0<sup>o<\/sup>C (specific latent heat of fusion of ice = 336x10<sup>3<\/sup>JKg<sup>-1<\/sup>)<\/strong><\/p>","options":["76.0mins","35.0mins","21.0mins","2.9mins"],"answerIndex":2,"examYear":"2006"},{"question":"<p><strong>200g of water at 90<sup>o<\/sup>C is mixed with 100g of water at 30<sup>o<\/sup>C. What is the final temperature?<\/strong><\/p>","options":["20<sup>o<\/sup>","60<sup>o<\/sup>","50<sup>o<\/sup>","10<sup>o<\/sup>"],"answerIndex":2,"examYear":"2006"},{"question":"<p><strong>The equation PVT = constant is Charles law when<\/strong><\/p>","options":["x=1, y=1, z=1","x=0, y=1, z=1","x=1, y=0, z=1","x=0, y=1, z=0"],"answerIndex":2,"examYear":"2006"},{"question":"<p><strong>For a short sighted person, light rays from a point on a very distant object is focused&nbsp;<\/strong><\/p>","options":["in front of the retina","behind the retina","behind the retina by a diverging lens","in front of the retina, a distance 2F from the lens"],"answerIndex":2,"examYear":"2006"},{"question":"<p><strong>Dispersion of light by a glass prism is due to the<\/strong><\/p>","options":["different hidden colours of the glass","different speeds of various colours in glass","defects in the glass","high density in glass"],"answerIndex":2,"examYear":"2006"},{"question":"<p><strong>To produce an enlargement and erect image with a concave mirror, the object must be positioned<\/strong><\/p>","options":["between the principal focus and the center curvature","at the principal focus","between the principal focus and the pole","beyond the center of curvature"],"answerIndex":3,"examYear":"2006"},{"question":"<p><strong>To convert an ac dynamo into a dc dynamo, the<\/strong><\/p>","options":["number of turns of the coil is increased","slipt rings are replaced with a split ring commutator","the coil is reduced","split ring commutator is replaced with slip rings"],"answerIndex":2,"examYear":"2006"},{"question":"<p><strong>In an a.c circuit, that contains only a capacitor, the voltage&nbsp;<\/strong><\/p>","options":["lags behind the current by 90<sup>o<\/sup>","loads the current by W","lags behind the current by 180<sup>o<\/sup>","leads the current by 180<sup>o<\/sup>"],"answerIndex":1,"examYear":"2006"},{"question":"<p><strong>The purpose of the dielectric material in a parallel plate capacitor is to<\/strong><\/p>","options":["increase its capacitance","decrease its capacitance","insulate the plates from each other","increase the magnetic field between plates"],"answerIndex":1,"examYear":"2006"},{"question":"<p><strong>A substance has a half life of 5mins. After 6mins, the count rate was observed to be 400. What was its count rate at zero time<\/strong><\/p>","options":["200","1200","1600","2400"],"answerIndex":4,"examYear":"2006"},{"question":"<p><strong>If light with proton energy 2ev is incident on the surface of a metal with work function 3ev. Then<\/strong><\/p>","options":["no electron will be emitted","the few electrons emitted will have maximum kinetic energy of 1ev","the few electrons emitted will have a maximum kinetic energy of 3ev","many electrons will be emitted with maximum kinetic energy of 5ev"],"answerIndex":1,"examYear":"2006"},{"question":"<p><strong>In a nuclear fusion experiment, the loss of mass amounts to 1.0 x 10<sup>6<\/sup>g. The amount of energy obtained from the fusion (speed of light 3.0 x 10<sup>3<\/sup> ms<sup>-1<\/sup>) is<\/strong><\/p>","options":["3.0 x 10<sup>-4<\/sup>J","5.0 x 10<sup>-1<\/sup>J","9.0 x 10<sup>4<\/sup>J","9.0 x 10<sup>-10<\/sup>J"],"answerIndex":4,"examYear":"2006"}]